Let me enthusiastically welcome you all back to week three of our LLM engineering journey.
LLM 엔지니어링 여정 3주 차에 오신 여러분을 열렬히 환영해 주세요
If you enjoyed last week when we got deep into building user interfaces using the fabulous Gradio framework,
지난주에 사용자 인터페이스를 구축하는 과정을 보셨다면 멋진 그래디오 프레임워크를
then you're going to love this week even more, because now it's time to get into open source and start
이용했죠 이번 주는 더 맘에 드실 겁니다 이제 오픈 소스를 시작해 포옹의 멋진
using the wonderful world of Huggingface.
세계를 사용할 시간이거든요
But first, a quick recap as always on what you can already do.
하지만 먼저 늘 그렇듯 이미 할 수 있는 걸 간단히 요약해보죠
You can describe Transformers and you are fluent in the key terminology.
트랜스포머를 묘사할 수 있고 핵심 용어도 유창하죠
You can talk about context windows until the cows come home and all of that.
컨텍스트 창문에 대해 얘기할 수 있어요
You can confidently code whether it's with Gemini or Claude or with OpenAI.
쌍둥이자리나 클로드 오픈아이든 자신 있게 코드를 짤 수 있어요
You know the APIs.
API 아시죠?
You know how to stream, you know about markdown, you know about JSON responses.
스트림도 알고 마크다운도 알고 JSON 반응도 알죠
And you can also build an AI assistant, a chatbot.
인공지능 비서인 챗봇도 만들 수 있어요
You can make it use tools.
도구를 사용해도 돼요
You can make it use different agents, and you can make it multimodal.
여러 에이전트를 사용할 수도 있고 멀티모덜로 만들 수도 있어요
And we've built one ourselves.
우리도 하나 지었죠
And hopefully you've extended it to.
그걸 확장했길 바라요
too.
저도요
So what's happening today?
오늘은 무슨 일이죠?
Today we're going to get into hugging face.
오늘은 얼굴 포옹을 배워볼 거예요 get it
And to start with, you're just going to be able to describe what it is and the scope and scale of hugging
먼저, 이게 무엇인지 설명하실 수 있을 겁니다 얼굴을 껴안는 것의 스코프와 규모도요
face.
얼굴을 안는 것의 가장 놀라운 점은 너비예요
All the different things that it offers to the open source data science community, and you'll have
오픈 소스 데이터 과학 커뮤니티에 제공하는 모든 다양한 것들이요 여러분도
a good appreciation for that shortly.
곧 그걸 잘 이해하게 될 거예요
Uh, we're going to look at models, data sets and spaces in hugging face, and you'll also have a good
모델과 얼굴을 포옹할 때 데이터 세트, 공간을 살펴볼 겁니다 구글 콜랩도 잘
understanding of Google Colab.
이해하게 될 거예요
You may already have an understanding of Google Colab, in which case it'll be a quick revision point.
구글 콜랍을 이미 이해했다면 빠른 복습 지점이 되겠죠
But for those that don't, we're going to go into it.
그렇지 않은 분들은 지금 살펴보죠
You're going to see how you can run code on a box with a good GPU, and you'll have a sense of the different
좋은 GPU 박스에서 코드를 실행하는 방법을 볼 겁니다 다양한 제공이 있고 어떤 걸 클래스에
offerings out there and which ones we'll be using for the class.
사용할지 알게 될 거예요
So we'll get you set up.
get up을 해드릴게요
So prepare for some open source stuff.
오픈 소스 준비하세요
But first, as always, a quick recap on what's been going on, where we are and what's left to do.
하지만 먼저, 현재 상황과 현재 위치, 남은 일을 간단히 정리해 보죠
We started on the left with uh, at the beginning, no LM engineering knowledge, we will end up on
왼쪽에서 출발해서 달 착륙선 엔지니어링 지식이 없었지만 능숙한 달 착륙선 엔지니어답게
the right as proficient LM engineers.
오른쪽에서 끝날 거예요
In week one, we got immersed in all things frontier.
첫 주에는 개척지 문화에 푹 빠져들었어요
In week two.
2주 차에요
Last week we built UIs.
지난주엔 UI를 만들었죠
We used all of the APIs for the top three and we experimented with tools.
상위 3개에 API를 모두 사용했고 도구로 실험했어요
Agent ization Multi-modality this week, all about open source, all about hugging face.
이번 주 에이전트 iization 다중 모듈은 오픈 소스와 얼굴 포옹에 관한 거죠
Next week we talk about selecting the right LM for the problem and generating code.
다음 주엔 문제에 맞는 LM을 선택하고 코드 생성하는 걸 얘기하죠
After that is Rag week.
그다음은 래그 주간이에요
Then we fine tune a frontier model, then we fine tune an open source model, and then in the finale
그 후 개척지 모델을 조정하고 오픈 소스 모델을 조정하고 피날레에서 전부 완성하는
we bring it all home.
거죠
So without further ado, let's talk hugging face.
그럼 지체 없이 포옹하는 얼굴 얘기를 해보죠
So as I say, it's ubiquitous.
유비쿼터스라고 할 수 있죠
It's it's used across the community.
지역 사회에서 사용되죠
It is a fabulous resource.
정말 훌륭한 자원이에요
And amongst many things, it offers us three the hugging face platform, the the what you get to if
무엇보다도 H깅 페이스 플랫폼이 세 가지 있습니다 H깅 페이스 코에 접속하면
you go to Hugging Face Co and you've signed up with an account.
계정을 만들 수 있죠
You have access to three categories of things.
세 가지 카테고리에 접근할 수 있어요
First of all, you have models over 800,000 open source models that can do a bunch of different types
우선 800,000개가 넘는 오픈 소스 모델이 있어요 다양한 작업을 수행할 수 있죠
of tasks, many of which we will experiment with in this week's lectures.
그중 상당수는 이번 주 강의에서 실험할 거예요
And in future weeks, there are data sets.
앞으로 몇 주간은 데이터 세트가 있어요
It is a treasure trove, over 200,000 data sets covering almost any problem that you can think of.
보물 창고입니다 200,000개가 넘는 데이터가 거의 모든 문제를 다루고 있죠
You can try searching and see what you find.
검색해 보고 뭐가 나오는지 보세요
We're going to be using one particularly amazing data set later in this course.
이 과정 후반부에 특히 놀라운 데이터 세트를 사용할 거예요
But but you will find lots of data to to solve your problems.
하지만 많은 데이터를 찾아서 문제를 해결할 수 있어요
Um, it's similar to to the platform Kaggle which is much more focused on the data side of things.
플랫폼 케이글과 비슷합니다 데이터 측면에 훨씬 더 집중하죠
But you have such a huge resource of that data within hugging face.
하지만 얼굴 한 번 안아도 데이터는 방대하죠
And then hugging face also has something called spaces, which is where you can write an app and expose
얼굴을 안는 것에는 스페이스라는 것이 있습니다 앱을 작성하고 공개할 수 있는 곳이죠
Have it running on hugging face cloud hardware and and available for other people to use.
페이스 클라우드 하드웨어를 끌어안고 다른 사람들이 사용할 수 있도록 하세요
As long as you're you're happy for your code to be open source, because that is the the you know,
코드가 오픈 소스인 게 좋다면 말이죠 왜냐하면 그게 포옹하는 얼굴의
that's what Hugging Face is all about.
의미니까요
Uh, so spaces are many of the spaces apps are written built in Gradio.
스페이스 앱은 많은 스페이스 앱이 그래디오로 만들어졌어요
So they are gradio apps.
그러디오 앱인 셈이죠
Um, there are things that are not gradio apps.
그러디오 앱이 아닌 것도 있어요
There's something called Streamlit, which is another way to build apps that is also quite magical.
스트림리츠라는 게 있는데 앱을 만드는 또 다른 방법인데 이것도 꽤 마법 같아요
Different to Gradio, quite magical.
그래디오와는 달라요 마법 같죠
Um, and there are some other ways that you can publish apps as well.
앱을 게시할 수 있는 다른 방법도 있어요
Uh, but I'd say Gradio is probably the most common that's there.
하지만 그라디오가 가장 흔한 것 같아요
And there's in particular things called leaderboards, which are gradio apps whose job it is to evaluate
그리고 leaderboard라는 것이 있는데 그러디오 앱으로 여러 llm을 평가하고 순위를
different llms and rank them and show them in a kind of scorecard.
매겨 점수표에 표시하는 역할을 하죠
We're going to be using leaderboards a lot when we look at comparing different llms and, but we'll
다른 llm들을 비교할 때 leaderboard를 많이 사용할
be seeing some of them today as well as we look at huggingface spaces.
거예요 오늘 몇 가지를 볼 겁니다 포옹표 공간도 보고요
So that's the Huggingface platform, which is what you get to if you go to Huggingface Co and log in
그게 허깅페이스 플랫폼입니다 허깅페이스 코에 로그인해 뭐가 있는지 살펴보면
and start looking at what's out there.
알 수 있죠
Hugging face also offers libraries code, which forms the basis of many of our open source projects.
얼굴을 안는 것은 라이브러리 코드도 제공합니다 우리 오픈 소스 프로젝트의 기초가 되는 코드죠
And the libraries give us this amazing head start in what we want to do.
그리고 라이브러리는 우리가 원하는 것에서 출발할 수 있게 해주죠. HDP, DBP, HDP, HD, HDP, HD, HDP, HD, HDP, HD, HDP, HD, HDP, HD, HD
It brings time to market much lower, because you can just be off and running very quickly with very
시장성이 훨씬 낮아지죠 아주 적은 상용 코드만으로도 아주 빨리 실행할
little boilerplate code.
수 있으니까요
It's the very well crafted libraries to reduce the barrier to entry and make people productive quickly.
아주 잘 만들어진 도서관으로 출입 장벽을 줄이고 사람들의 생산력을 높여주죠
The one of the first libraries you'll experience is the Hugging Face Hub, which is a library that allows
여러분이 경험할 첫 라이브러리 중 하나는 페이스 허브입니다
you to log in to hugging face and, uh, both download and upload things like data sets and models from
얼굴을 안는 데 로그인할 수 있는 라이브러리로서 허브에서 데이터 세트와 모델 같은 걸 다운로드 및 업로드
the hub, which is what hugging face calls the platform we just talked about.
할 수 있습니다 얼굴을 안는 플랫폼이라고 부르는 거죠
Um, data sets is a library that gives us access, immediate access to, uh, the, the the data repositories
데이터 집합은 라이브러리 같은 거예요 즉각적인 접근이 가능하죠 포옹이나 트랜스포머에
in hugging Huggingface and Transformers.
관한 데이터 저장소 같은 거요
This is a central library, which is the wrapper code around Llms that follow the transformer architecture,
이건 중앙 라이브러리인데 변압기 아키텍처를 따라가는 ㄹm을 감싸는 코드죠 그 밑에는 이런
and under the covers it's got either PyTorch or TensorFlow code that actually runs these neural networks.
신경망 네트워크를 실행하는 PyToch나 텐서플로우 코드가 있어요
But when you create a transformer, you have the actual deep neural network code at your fingertips.
하지만 변압기를 만들 때 손끝에 심층 신경망 코드가 있어요
When we make calls to functions, to methods in transformer code, we're no longer calling out to an
함수나 변압기 코드의 메서드에 호출을 할 때 오픈AI의 범주 내 다른
API running on a cloud somewhere else under OpenAI's umbrella.
클라우드에서 실행되는 API를 호출하지 않아요
We are executing the code ourselves to to execute to either inference or training against our deep neural
우리가 직접 코드를 실행하는 건 심층 신경망에 대한 추론이나 훈련에 실행하기 위해서죠
So there are three other libraries that I wanted to mention that we're going to come to later in the
언급하고 싶은 다른 라이브러리가 세 개 더 있어요 과정의 나중에
course that are more advanced libraries.
좀 더 고급 라이브러리예요
Um, the first of them, Peft, stands for parameter efficient fine tuning.
첫 번째는 페프트인데 매개 변수 효율 미세 조정의 약자죠
And this is, uh, utilities which allow us to train llms without needing to work with all of the billions
이 유틸리티 덕분에 수십억 개의 변수를 다루지 않고 llm을
of parameters in the Llms.
훈련할 수 있죠
So it's parameter efficient.
매개 변수 효율이죠
And the technique in particular that we'll be using is called Laura or Laura is a variation of Laura,
특히 우리가 사용할 기술은 로라라고 하는데 로라의 변형이죠
and there'll be plenty of time to explain that later on.
나중에 설명할 시간은 많아요
But but bear in mind that's what we'll be using.
하지만 우리가 사용할 거라는 걸 명심하세요
And it's part of the Peft library parameter efficient fine tuning.
페프트 라이브러리 매개 변수 효율적인 미세 조정의 일부죠
Then there's a library called Treal, which stands for Transformer Reinforcement Learning.
트리알이라는 라이브러리도 있는데 트랜스포머 강화 학습의 약자죠
And it includes a few things.
몇 가지 조건이 있어요
It's the ability to do things like something called reward modeling.
보상 모델링 같은 걸 하는 능력이죠
Mm.
네
And it's also something called proximal policy optimization PPO.
최측근 정책 최적화 PPO라고도 하죠
And you may see mm and PPO mentioned from time to time.
음미로와 PPO에 대해 가끔 언급하실 텐데요
And this is related to uh, the both this thing called WRF that I mentioned a while ago, and it's the
이건 앞서 언급한 WRF와 관련이 있어요 더 나은 후속
successors better ways of doing it, which is how we are able to train LMS so that they are really effective
방식이죠 LMS를 훈련하는 방법이요 채팅에서 효과적이죠
And it was the key innovation that resulted in ChatGPT in late 2022.
2022년 말 챗GPT가 탄생한 핵심 혁신이었죠
So a lot of that code is within TRL.
많은 코드가 TRL 내에 있어요
Also within TRL is something called supervised fine tuning and SFT, and that is something we will directly
TRL에는 감독 미세 조정과 SFT라는 게 있는데 나중에 코스에서도 직접
use ourselves later in the course.
사용할 거예요
That is the specific library we will be using to fine tune an open source model, so that it's even
오픈 소스 모델을 조정하기 위해 사용하는 라이브러리입니다 특정 문제가
more effective in our particular domain with a particular problem.
있는 특정 도메인에서 더 효과적으로요
We will set it so SFT supervised fine tuning part of the TRL library.
TRL 라이브러리의 미세한 조율을 담당했죠
All these acronyms.
전부 두문자어예요
SFT part of TRL uh and the it's a it's an essential framework.
TRL의 일부예요 아주 중요한 프레임워크죠
But this is some of the more advanced stuff we'll get back to.
이건 좀 더 고급이죠 나중에 다시 올게요 Get in get
So you don't have to remember all that right now, and certainly don't have to remember all these acronyms,
지금 당장 다 외울 필요는 없어요 이 약어들도 확실히 기억할 필요는
but just let me plant that seed in you so that when you see it later, it's something that you've heard
없고요 하지만 제가 그 씨앗을 심어서 나중에 봤을 때 이미 들어본 것으로 만들게요
The other one is one that is more of a behind the scenes, but you'll often see us importing it and
다른 하나는 무대 뒤의 것에 더 가깝지만 불러와서 이용하는 걸 종종 보실
making some use of it.
수 있어요
It's called accelerate, and it's some, uh, advanced huggingface code that allows, uh, that allows
가속이라고 하는데 고급 안기체 코드예요 어떤 분산 구성에서도 트랜스포머가
our transformers to run across any distributed configuration.
작동할 수 있게 해 주죠
So it allows both training and inference to run at scale in an efficient, adaptable way, potentially
훈련과 추론 둘 다 가능합니다 효율적이고 적응성 있는 방법으로 여러 GPU에 걸쳐 실행할
across multiple GPUs.
수 있도록요
Although in all the experiments we'll be doing, we'll only be using a maximum of one GPU.
우리가 할 실험은 최대 1개의 GPU로 진행되지만요
So those are some of the key libraries that sit behind hugging face.
얼굴을 껴안는 것 뒤에 있는 주요 라이브러리예요
At this point.
지금은요
I think it's time that we get to look at hugging face.
Get it get 이제 포옹하는 모습을 볼 때가 됐어요
So let's go in and take some some browsing around, starting with the hugging face platform.
그럼 좀 둘러보죠 포옹하는 얼굴 플랫폼부터요